Dr. B.P. Bijay Sankar

Flat No- A4/103, Jagannath Warrior Residency, Kaimatia, Madanpur, Bhubaneswar, Odisha-752054

Mobile:+91-7008221639/ 9438145236 ⊠Email: bpbijaysankar@gmail.com



Career Objective

To excel in teaching, research and academic administration. Intend to build my career with a leading organisation, which will help me to explore my potential. Aim to learn, lead, serve and bring smiles to millions through my teaching and research.

Academic Qualification

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD)	National Institute of Technology Rourkela, Odisha, India.	(2014-2019)
Masters in Commerce (Finance Honours)	Ravenshaw University, Odisha, India. Secured 70% mark (1 st division)	(2010-2012)
CA Inter (gr-1)	Institute of Chartered Accountants of India (ICAI)	(2010)
Bachelor of Commerce (Accounting Honours)	BJB Autonomous College, Utkal University, Odisha, India. Secured 65% mark (1st division with distinction)	(2006-2009)
Intermediate in Commerce	BJB Junior College, Council of Higher Secondary Education, Odisha, India. Secured 72% mark (1 st division)	(2004-2006)
Matriculation	Board of Secondary Education, Odisha, India. Secured 75% mark (1 st division)	(2004)

Technical Qualification

- Certificate course on Forensic Accounting and Fraud Examination from West Virginia University through Coursera.
- Information Technology Training (ITT) program from Institute of Chartered Accountants of India, Bhubaneswar Branch in the year 2010.
- Orientation program from Institute of Chartered Accountants of India, Bhubaneswar branch in the year 2010.
- Computer training course (100 hours) from Institute of Cost Accountants of India, Bhubaneswar branch in the year 2010.

Teaching Experience

- Currently Working as Lecturer in Commerce Jatni College, Jatni,
 Under Higher Education Department, Government of Odisha.
- Assistant Professor (2nd January, 2019 1st June 2022)
 Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University, Bhubaneswar, Odisha
- Assistant Professor (7th September, 2018- 25th December, 2018)
 Sri Sri University, Cuttack, Odisha, India
- Teaching Assistant (July, 2014 July 2018)

School of Management

National Institute of Technology Rourkela, Odisha, India.

Private Tutor (July, 2012 - June, 2014)
 Institute of Commerce (Private coaching center), Bhubaneswar, Odisha.

Research Experience

• Full time PhD Scholar (2014 - 2018)

Title of the Thesis: Payment Methods and Shareholders' Gains in Mergers and Acquisitions: An Empirical Investigation into Indian Companies.

Supervisor: **Dr. N. M. Leepsa**, Assistant Professor, School of Management, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.

Project fellow (Field Assistant) (Nov, 2015 - March, 2016)

Project: Impact assessment of CSR activities for Talcher and IB Coalfields of MCL. Principal investigator: **Dr. Chandan Kumar Sahoo**, Associate Professor, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.

- **Guided,** MBA final year Students (18 Nos.) for dissertation work in the area of finance, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- Guided, M.Com Students (14 Nos.) and B.Com final year Students (34 Nos.) for Summer Internship Program, Birla School of Commerce.

Research/Teaching Interest Area

Research Interest

- Mergers and Acquisition
- Stock Market
- Business Valuation
- Corporate finance

Teaching Interest

- Financial and Cost Accounting
- Management Accounting
- Corporate Restructuring
- o Financial Management
- Business Statistics
- Financial Statement Analysis and Reporting
- Business Research Methodology

Awards and Recognitions

 Felicitation by Honorable Vice Chancellor, Prof. P. P. Mathur and Esteemed Registrar, Prof. B.K. Das, Birla Global University for invaluable contribution towards Quality Education.

- **Doctoral Fellowship** award from the Indian Council of Social Science Research (ICSSR) to carry out Ph.D. work.
- State-level chess player award from All Odisha Chess Association (AOCA).
- Best Student award for social work in the year of 2005 from BJB Junior College, Bhubaneswar.
- Chief Prefect award from Vikram Sarabhai Hall of Residence, NIT Rourkela.

Membership of Professional Associations

- Indian Finance Association (IFA)
- Center for Global Transformation (CGFT)

Publications

Journals (Published)

- 1. **Sankar, B.P.B., &** Leepsa, N.M. (2022). Payment Methods and Shareholders' Gains in Mergers and Acquisitions: An Empirical Investigation into Indian Companies. *Finance India*, *36* (1), 343-352. (Scopus indexed and ABDC- C Category).
- Mahajan, M., Bhanawat, H., Sankar, B.P.B., & Sharma, J.K. (2022). Competencies and Organizational culture: An impact analysis to determine Managerial Effectiveness. *International Journal of Business Excellence*. (Inderscience Publishers & Scopus indexed) (forthcoming) DOI: 10.1504/IJBEX.2021.10044477
- 3. **Sankar, B.P.B.,** & Leepsa, N.M. (2021). Determinants of Payment Method in Mergers and Acquisitions: A Study on Indian Companies. *Indian Journal of Finance*. *15* (10), 44-62. DOI: 10.17010/ijf/2021/v15i10/166511. (Scopus indexed and ABDC- C Category).
- 4. Lavanya, S., **Sankar B.P.B.**, & Bhanawat, H. (2021). COVID-19 Pandemic Toll on Service Sector in India. *Sharing Economy: National and International Strategies, Empirical Economics Letters*. 20(2). (ABDC- C Category).
- 5. Kaur P, **Sankar B.P.B.**, & Bhanawat H. (2020) Foreign Institutional Investor and Stock Market Volatility: Evidence from India. *Test Engineering and Management.84*, 9574 9585. http://www.testmagzine.biz/index.php/testmagzine/article/view/2361.
- 6. **Sankar, B.P.B.,** & Leepsa, N. M. (2019). Bank Mergers: Opportunity or Obstruction? An Indian Case Study. *Singapore Management Journal*, 8(1), 63-80.
- 7. **Sankar, B.P.B.**, & Leepsa, N. M. (2018). Payment Methods in Acquisitions: A Study on Short-Term Performance of Indian Acquiring Firms. *Indian Journal of Research in Capital Markets*, 5(2), 7-22. DOI: 10.17010//ijrcm/2018/v5/i2/130185.
- 8. **Sankar, B.P.B.**, & Leepsa, N. M. (2018). Payment Methods in Mergers and Acquisitions: A Theoretical Framework. *International Journal of Accounting and Financial Reporting*, 8(1), 170-187. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5296/ijafr.v8i1.12354.
- 9. **Sankar, B.P.B.**, Dash, P., & Leepsa, N. M. (2018). Is Demonetisation a Bridge for Digital Financial Inclusion: An Extensive Survey. *IIMS Journal of Management Science*, 9(2), 93-99. DOI:10.5958/0976-173X.2018.00009.X

Patents

- ♣ 2021: Published Indian Patent on "Artificial Intelligence Based Method and Process of Collecting Financial Transaction Data" (Application No.: 202211055680, Date of Application: 28/09/2022)
- **↓** 2021: Published Indian Patent on "Account and Financial Management Technology" (Application No.: 202111035179, Date of Application: 04/08/2021)
- ♣ 2021: Granted Australian Patent on "System and method for monitoring post covid patient using machine learning and block chain" (Application No.: 202111035179, Date of Granted: 19/08/2021)

Book Chapters

- 1. Kaur, P., Bijay Sankar, B.P., Bhanawat, H. (2022). A Descriptive Study on the Assessment of Flows by Foreign Institutional Investment. Business and Economics, Economic Issues, Problems and Perspectives, Economics, Business, & Finance, Finance and Investments, International Finance, Nova, Social Sciences Publications. (ISBN: 978-1-68507-838-6). https://doi.org/10.52305/ERPO8430
- Kaur, P., Bijay Sankar, B.P., Bhanawat, H. (2022). Effects of Covid-19 Lockdown: A Perception Survey. In: Yadav, S., Haleem, A., Arora, P.K., Kumar, H. (eds) Proceedings of Second International Conference in Mechanical and Energy Technology. Smart Innovation, Systems and Technologies, vol 290 (pp 529–538). Springer, Singapore. (ISBN: 978-981-19-0107-2) https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-19-0108-9-54 (Scopus indexed).
- 3. Bhanawat H, Bijay Sankar B.P. and Pandey G (2020) Diversification of Agriculture and Impact on Farmers' Income. Business Interventions for Effective Management of Technology and Innovation. Indian Institute of Management (IIM), Sirmaur India [Wiley]

Presented Paper in Conferences

International

- 1. Lavanya, S., & **Sankar, B. P. B**. (2021) "Service Sector in India: Pre and Post COVID-19 Era" in *International Management Conference on Post COVID Management Strategies: Recovery, Resilience & Adaptation*, 23rd- 24th April, 2021 organised by Indian Institute of Management Bodh Gaya.
- 2. **Sankar, B. P. B.,** Bhanawat, H. & Dash, A.K. (2019) "Mega Merger Announcement in Banking Sector: An Analysis of Short-Term Performance" in *International Conference on Global Trends in Business Practices and Management Education*, 24th -25th January 2019 at Hotel The Crown, Bhubaneswar, Odisha, organised by Birla Global University.
- 3. Lavanya, S., Sharma, A.R. & Sankar, B. P. B. (2019) "Mega Merger of Banks: A Study of Customer Perspective" in *International Conference on Global Trends in Business*

- *Practices and Management Education*, 24th -25th January 2019 at Hotel The Crown, Bhubaneswar, Odisha, organised by Birla Global University.
- 4. **Sankar, B. P. B.**, & Leepsa, N. M. (2016). "Choice of Payment Methods in Mergers and Acquisitions: Review and Reappraisal of Past Empirical Research" in *International Conference on Financial Markets and Corporate Finance*, 12th-13th August 2016 at Chennai: Department of Management Studies, Indian Institute of Technology Madras.
- 5. Dash,P.,& **Sankar**, **B. P.B.**,(2017)."Corporate Restructuring through Spin-off: A Journey of Max Group towards Excellence" in *International Conference on Financial Markets and Corporate Finance*, 7th 8th July 2017 at Kharagpur: Vinod Gupta School of Management, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur.

National

- 1. **Sankar, B. P. B.** (2019). "Impact of M&A Announcement on Stock Returns of Acquirer: Listing Status of Target" in *National Seminar on Indian Financial System: Strategic Issues, Challenges and Opportunities*, 18th October 2019 at Birla Global University campus in Bhubaneswar.
- 2. Tasnim, S. & **Sankar**, **B. P. B.**(2019) "Corporate governance failure: A case study on IL&FS" in *National Seminar on Economic Development: Rationality vs Populism*, 09th 10thJanuary 2019 at Birla Global University campus in Bhubaneswar.
- 3. Lavanya, S., Sharma, A.R. & **Sankar, B. P. B.** (2019) "Impact of deficit finance and Inflation on Indian Economy" in *National Seminar on Economic Development: Rationality vs Populism*, 09th -10thJanuary 2019 at Birla Global University campus in Bhubaneswar.
- 4. **Sankar, B. P. B.**, & Leepsa, N. M. (2017). "Guidelines of New Companies Act 2013 and Their Effect on Merger & Acquisition in India" in *National Management Conclave on "Business, Innovation & Sustainability"*, 7th 8th January 2017 at Rourkela: School of Management, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 5. **Sankar, B. P. B.**, & Leepsa, N. M. (2017). "ACriticalAnalysisUnionBudget2017-18" in the seminar on *UnionBudget2017-18: Perception and Reality*, 15th March 2017 at Rourkela: School of Management, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 6. Pratihari, S. & **Sankar, B. P. B.**,(2017). "Demonetization in the Fourth Pillar of Indian Democracy: A Content Analysis" in the seminar on *Demonetization: Personal Narratives and Political Motifs*, 10th February 2017 at Rourkela: Department of Humanities and Social Sciences, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 7. **Sankar**, **B. P.B.** (2009). "Standard Costing: A Control Technique" in *National Conference for CA Students* in the year 2009, at Bhubaneswar: The Institute of Chartered Accountant of India (ICAI) Bhubaneswar Branch.

Poster Presentation

1. Sankar, B. P. B., & Leepsa, N. M.(2017). "Is Demonetization a Bridge for Digital

Financial Inclusion: An Extensive Survey" in *Fifth Pan IIM World Management Conference*, 14th - 16th December 2017 at Indian Institute of Management Lucknow Campus.

Conferences/ FDPs/ Workshops/ Seminars / Certificate Course Conducted

- 1. Conducted an One Week **Faculty Development Programme** on "Methodology for Advanced Research and Quality Publication" from 21st to 25th March, 2022 at Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University, Bhubaneswar.
- 2. Introduced and Coordinated a three months **Certificate Course** on "Financial Planning and Investment Management" at Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University. Two Times- (February to May 2021), (Novemver 2021 to January 2022).
- 3. Coordinated a joint **Webinar** on the topic "Business Responsibility and Sustainability Reporting" organised by Birla School of Commerce and The Institute of Chartered Accountants of India, Bhubaneswar Chapter on 27th September, 2021.
- 4. Organized a **Faculty Development Programme** on "Advance Research Methodology for Decision-Making" on 15th and 16th December, 2020 at Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University.
- 5. Coordinated a **Webinar** on 'Atmanirbhar Bharat: Opportunities Unlimited' on 25th August 2020 organized by Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University.
- 6. Coordinated a **National Seminar** on Indian Financial System: Strategic Issues, Challenges and Opportunities on 18th October, 2019 organized by Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University.
- 7. Coordinated a **Financial Modelling Workshop** 29th & 30th August, 2019 organized by Birla School of Commerce, Birla Global University.

Academic and Administration duties

- 1. Course Coordinator of B.Com Programme from September 2021 to May 2022 at Birla School of Commerce.
- 2. Course Coordinator of Ph.D. Programme from July 2020 to May 2022 at Birla School of Commerce.
- 3. Examination Superintendent of Birla School of Commerce for semester examinations of BSoC in the academic year 2020-2021.
- 4. Member of Board of Studies, Birla School of Commerce.
- 5. Member of Finance Committee, Birla Global University.
- 6. Member of Library Committee at Birla Global University in the academic year 2021-2022.
- 7. Member of Alumni Committee at Birla Global University in the academic year 2021-2022.

Seminar and Workshops Attended

1. Workshop on "How to Write and Publish Scientific Articles and Manuscripts", 7th March 2018, jointly organised by Springer Nature and National Institute of Technology Rourkela.

- 2. "A Three-Day Short Term Course on Panel Data Analysis Using Stata", 23th 25th November 2016, organised by Department of Humanities and Social Sciences National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 3. "A Four Day Short Term Course (STC) on Time Series Modelling and Forecasting: Using Eviews Package", 27th 30th January 2016, organised by Department of Humanities and Social Sciences National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 4. "Financial Research Workshop", 18th 19th November 2016, organised by Indian Institute of Management Calcutta.
- 5. "A Four Day Short Term Course (STC) on Time Series Modelling and Forecasting: Using Eviews Package", 27th 30th January 2016, organised by Department of Humanities and Social Sciences National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 6. "5th Indian Finance Conference", 16th December 2015 organised by Indian Institute of Management Calcutta.
- 7. "Intellectual property & Innovation Management in Knowledge Era", 24th November 2015, organised by National Research Development Corporation, New Delhi.
- 8. "A four-Day Short Term Course on Fundamentals of Applied Econometrics Using Stata", 28th September 01th October 2015, organised by Department of Humanities and Social Sciences National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 9. "Certificate Program on Research Methodology", 29th 30th June 2015, organised by Asian School of Business Management, Bhubaneswar.
- 10. "Analytical Hierarchy Process and Data Envelopment Analysis", 18th March 2015, organized by School of Management, National Institute of Technology Rourkela.
- 11. ICSSR sponsored workshop on "Multivariate Data Analysis", 08th 09th November 2014, organized by Indian Institute for Production Management, Kansbahal, Rourkela.

Faculty Development Programme and Refresher Programme Participated

- 1. Annual Refresher Course in Commerce, February 2020, organized by MHRD, Government of India.
- 2. Annual Refresher Course on "Financial Markets and Emerging Business Models", February 2020, organized by MHRD, Government of India.
- 3. One Week Short Term Training Program on "Advance Technique in Research and Data Analytical Tools by using SPSS and Eviews" 23rd 28th November, 2020, organized by Meerut Institute of Engineering & Technology, Meerut, India. (AICTE Sponsored).
- 4. Faculty Development Programme on "Outcome-Based Learning and Case Writing" 7th -9th December 2019, organized by Birla School of Management, Birla Global University, Bhubaneswar.
- 5. "Capacity Building Workshop for Faculty Member of Management and Social Sciences", 17th
 29th February 2016, organized by School of Management and Humanities and Social Sciences department of National Institute of Technology Rourkela.

Personal Details

Father's Name : Late Basanta Kumar Behura

Date of Birth : 08thJuly1989

Gender : Male
Nationality : Indian
Religion : Hindu
Marital Status : Married

References

1. Prof. N. M. Leepsa

Assistant Teaching Professor in Business, Arizona State University at Lake Havasu City,

Arizona - 86403, United States.

2. Prof. Rajeev Kumar Panda

Associate Professor, School of Management, National Institute of Technology Rourkela, India.

3. Prof. Pradyot Keshari Pradhan

Retd., Professor, Utkal University,

Bhubaneswar, Odisha.

Email: leepsa.madhabika@asu.edu

n.m.leepsa@gmail.com

Phone: (928) 854-9739 (O)

(623) 201-9594 (M)

Email: rkpanda@nitrkl.ac.in

Phone: (+91) - 0661-2462803 (O)

(+91) - 9437490180 (M)

Email: pradyotkp@mail.com

Phone: (+91) - 9437632197 (M)

Declaration

I do hereby declare that all the information furnished above are true and correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Date:15.02.2023

Place: Bhubaneswar

Dr. B.P. BIJAY SANKAR

B.P. Bijay Sarkan